Finding Aid for Paul Blanshard Papers, 1912-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul Blanshard papers 1912-1979
Blanshard, Paul, 1892-
851649 Aa/2
Author and social and religious commentator. Papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, scrapbooks and drafts of articles and books, and other papers, including material concerning his student years at the University of Michigan, as Congregational minister, educational director of the Amalgamated Textile Workers of America, assistant editor of The Nation, chief of the New York City Department of Investigations and Accounts under Fiorello La Guardia in the 1930's, economic analyst for the Caribbean Committee of the U.S. State Department during World War II, and free lance writer noted for his observations on the Catholic Church in America and abroad.
30.3 linear feet
0.99 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The major portion of the collection was received from Paul Blanshard in 1971. Additional materials came to the library in 1974 and 1982. Donor no. 5116
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Paul B. Blanshard was an author and a noted social and religious commentator, perhaps best known for his book American Freedom and Catholic Power. Blanshard was born in Fredericksburg, Ohio in 1892. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1914 then did graduate work at Harvard, Columbia, and Union Theological Seminary. He was ordained a congregational minister in 1917 and served a brief period as pastor of a church in Tampa, Florida. In 1918, Blanshard left the ministry for the trade union movement. From 1920 to 1924 he was educational director for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America in Rochester, New York, and in 1925 he served as field secretary of the League for Industrial Democracy, which position he held until 1933.
With the depression, Blanshard became increasingly involved with issues of urban reform. From 1930 to 1933, he served as executive director of the City Affairs Committee of New York City. Here he led investigations on the problem of municipal corruption and this eventually led to a position with the reform-minded La Guardia administration. During World War II, Blanshard worked as an economic analyst and consultant to the Caribbean Commission of the Department of State. He left in 1946 to become a full-time writer.
The subject that most exercised Blanshard as a writer was the Roman Catholic Church, particularly its political power and influence. In Blanshard's view, according to one writer, the Roman Catholic Church was "institutionally antithetical to democracy and politically antagonistic to American pluralism and individual liberty." Blanshard was most vehement in his denunciation of the church's hierarchy which he felt used its power in the United States to control policy on matters of education, social issues, and foreign affairs. Blanshard expatiated this theme in several books, the most important of these being American Freedom and Catholic Power published in 1949.
Blanshard was married three times. In 1915, he married Julia Sweet Anderson who died in 1934. In 1935, he married Mary Hillyer Kolski who died in 1965, and in 1965, he married Beatrice Mayer. Blanshard had two sons, Paul Blanshard, Jr. (b. 1919) and Rufus (b. 1921), and a twin brother (Percival) Brand Blanshard, a prominent professor of philosophy at Yale University. Blanshard died in St. Petersburg, Florida, in 1980.
For more detailed biographical information, the researcher should consult Blanshard's autobiography Personal and Controversial (1974). There are also files in the collection containing biographical and genealogical information (see Summary Content List).
Summary Contents List
Correspondence, 1892-1973 (boxes 1-4)
Writings and Related Materials
Articles and Speeches, 1917-1974 (boxes 4-5)
Book Reviews, 1928-1968 (box 5)
Journal Articles (box 5)
From the Church and State Newsletter, 1955-1962
From The Humanist, 1958-1965
Books and Pamphlets, c. 1920-1974 (box 6)
Background Files for Books/Post-Publication Materials
Democracy and Empire in the Caribbean, 1947 (box 11)
American Freedom and Catholic Power, 1949 (boxes 12-14)
Communism, Democracy and Catholic Power, 1952 (box 14)
The Irish and Catholic Power, 1954 (boxes 14-16)
The Right To Read, 1975 (boxes 17-18)
God and Man in Washington, 1960 (boxes 19-20)
Freedom and Catholic Power in Spain and Portugal, 1962 (boxes 21-22)
Religion and the Schools, 1963 (boxes 23-24)
Paul Blanshard on Vatican II 1966 (boxes 25-28)
Personal and Controversial, 1973 (box 28)
Some of My Best Friends are Christians, 1974 (box 28)
Background materials for speeches and articles (box 7)
Biographical Information
Books and pamphlets on Paul Blanshard (box 7)
Books and pamphlets on religious themes (include some with comments by or about Paul Blanshard) (box 7)
Clippings/scrapbooks (mainly about Paul Blanshard) (boxes 8-10)
Personal and miscellaneous (box 29)
Sound Recordings (box 31 and phonograph disc collection)
Photographs (box 31)
Julia Anderson Blanshard papers (box 30)
Mary Hillyer Blanshard papers (box 30)
The Paul Blanshard papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, drafts of articles and books, and speeches. The papers covering the period of 1912 to 1974 document the variety of Blanshard's life: his student years at the University of Michigan (1910-1914), his career as Congregational minister in East Boston, Massachusetts and Tampa, Florida (1917-1918), his work as educational director of the Amalgamated Textile and Clothing Workers of America in Rochester and Utica, New York (1900-1924), as secretary and lecturer of the League for Industrial Democracy (1924-1933), as correspondent and associate editor of The Nation (1928-1929), as director of the City Affairs Committee of New York (1930-1933) and head of the New York Department of Investigations and Accounts under Mayor Fiorello La Guardia (1934-1938), as director of the Society for the Prevention of Crime (1941-1942), as senior economic analyst and consultant to the director of the Caribbean Commission of the U.S. Department of State; and as freelance writer and critic of the Roman Catholic Church in America and abroad. The Blanshard collection also includes papers of his first wife Julia Blanshard and his second wife Mary Hillyer Blanshard.
The collection has been arranged into seven series: Correspondence; Writings and Related Materials; Biographical Information; Sound Recordings; Photographs; Julia Anderson Blanshard papers; and Mary Hillyer Blanshard papers.
Subjects:
Birth control.; Blanshard, Paul, 1892-1980; Catholic Church.; Clergy--United States.; Latin America.; League for Industrial Democracy.; The nation.; New York (N.Y.). City Affairs Committee.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Investigation.; Religion.; Society for the Prevention of Crime.; Strikes and lockouts--Clothing trade.; United States. Dept. of State.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Demonstrations.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Women.
Contributors:
Ad Hoc Committee to Lift Ban on The Nation.; Adler, Julius Ochs, 1892-1955.; Affiliated Summer Schools for Women Workers in Industry.; Aiken, George D. (George David), 1892-1984.; Allport, Gordon W. (Gordon Willard), 1897-1967.; America First Committee.; American Civil Liberties Union.; American Genetic Association.; American Humanist Association.; American Jewish Committee.; American Jewish Congress.; Amory, Cleveland.; Anderson, Jack, 1922-2005; Archer, Glenn Leroy, 1906-; Argoff, Charles, 1902-; Arnold, Melvin Luxton, 1913-; Arthur, William Bolling, 1914-; Axtelle, George E. (George Edward), 1893-1974.; Bain, Read, 1892-; Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1886-1960.; Beacon Press.; Bennett, Wallace F. (Wallace Foster), 1898-1993; Benson, Ezra Taft.; Biddle, Francis, 1886-1968.; Birkhead, Leon Milton, 1885-1954.; Blanshard, Brand, 1892-1987.; Blanshard, Mary Hillyer, d. 1965.; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977.; Bowie, Walter Russell, 1882-1969.; Brameld, Theodore, 1904-1987; Broun, Heywood, 1888-1939.; Brown, Francis, 1903-1995; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971.; Burdett, Winston, 1913-1993; Burns, James MacGregor.; Caldwell, John T. (John Tyler), 1911-1995; Chalmers, Allan Knight, 1897-; Chamberlin, William Henry, 1897-1969.; Chambers, David Laurance, b. 1879.; Clothier, Florence, 1903-; Cogley, John.; Collier, John, 1884-1968.; Conference for Progressive Labor Action.; Cousins, Norman.; Cowley, W. H. (William Harold), 1899-1978; Dawson, Joseph Martin, 1879-; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dickinson, Robert Latou, 1861-1950; Douglas, Emily.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Edwards, George, 1914-; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Eliot, Frederick May, 1889-1958.; Evans, Bergen, 1904-1978; Fairchild, Henry Pratt, 1880-1956.; Fey, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1898-1990; Fischer, John, 1910-; Flanders, Ralph E. (Ralph Edward), 1880-1970.; Flynn, John Thomas, 1883-1964.; Foote, Henry Wilder, 1875-1964.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Freethinkers of America.; Friends of Democracy (U.S); Gallup, George, 1901-1984; Gannett, Lewis, 1891-1966.; Gibson, Ernest W., 1901-1969.; Gilbert, Charles Kendall, 1878-1958.; Givens, Willard Earl, 1886-1971.; Goldman, Eric Frederick, 1915-1989; Greeley, Dana McLean, 1908-1986; Green, William, 1870-1952.; Gruening, Ernest, 1887-1974.; Gunther, John, 1901-1970.; Hall, Frank A., 1894-1972.; Hardman, J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky), 1882-1968.; Harrington, Donald.; Harrison, Gilbert A., 1915-; Hartman, Carl Gottfried, 1879-1968.; Hays, Arthur Garfield, 1881-1954.; Hechinger, Fred M.; Henry, Carl F. H. (Carl Ferdinand Howard), 1913-2003; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964.; Human Betterment Association of America.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Hunt, Alma, 1909-; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977; Hutchinson, Paul, 1890-1956.; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975.; Independent Voters for Norman Thomas.; Institute of Ethnic Affairs.; International Committee on Planned Parenthood.; International Planned Parenthood Federation.; James, Edwin Leland, 1890-1951.; Jones, Bob, 1911-1997; Jones, Howard Mumford, 1892-1980; Kallen, Horace Meyer, 1882-1974.; Keep America Out of War Congress.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Kirchwey, Freda.; Kirstein, George G.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Kunstler, William M. (William Moses), 1919-1995; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987.; La Piana, George, 1879-1971.; Lasker, Bruno, 1880-1965.; Latham, Harold Strong, 1887-1969.; Lathrop, John Howland, 1880-1967.; League for Fair Play.; League of Women Shoppers.; Lee, Alfred McClung, 1906-; Lee, Jennie.; Leiper, Henry Smith, 1891-1975; Lerner, Max, 1902-1992; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013; Lipphard, William B. (William Benjamin), b. 1886.; Livingston, Goodhue, 1867-1951.; Lodge, John Davis, 1903-1985.; Lord, John Wesley, 1902-; Lovett, Robert Morss, 1870-1956.; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967.; Lyons, Louis Martin, 1897-1982; McGraw, Harold Whittlesey, 1918-; MacGregor, Frank Silver, 1897-1971.; Mackay, John Alexander, 1889-1983; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Mallett, Reginald, 1893-1965.; Matthews, Herbert Lionel, 1900-; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Miller, Clyde R. (Clyde Raymond), 1888-1958; Moehlman, Conrad Henry, b. 1879.; Monroney, Mike, 1902-; Moore, Hugh, 1887-1972.; Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967.; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Nader, Ralph, 1934-; National Council on Freedom From Censorship.; Neuberger, Maurine B. (Maurine Brown), 1907-2000; Non-Partisan Committee for Harry W. Laidler for City Council.; O'Dwyer, William, 1890-1964.; Oxnam, G. Bromley (Garfield Bromley), 1891-1963.; Peale, Norman Vincent, 1898-1993; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.; Phillips, Thomas Wharton, 1874-1956.; Pike, James A. (James Albert), 1913-1969.; Pitkin, Walter Boughton, 1878-1953.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Poling, Daniel A. (Daniel Alfred), 1884-1968.; Post War World Council.; Poteat, Edwin McNeill, 1892-1955.; Potofsky, Jacob S. (Jacob Samuel), 1894-1979; Protestants and Other Americans United for Separation of Church and State.; Raines, Richard Campbell, 1898-; Reuther, Victor G. (Victor George), 1912-2004; Rice, Paul North, 1888-1967.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rose, David Kenneth, 1902-1963.; Rugg, Harold Ordway, 1886-1960.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966.; Saxe, Karl, 1892-; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Schroeder, John Charles, 1897-1954.; Seabury, Samuel, 1873-1958.; Shapiro, Rose.; Sheen, Fulton J. (Fulton John), 1895-1979.; Shipler, Guy Emery, 1881-; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Society for Ethical Culture (New York, N.Y.); Sorensen, Theodore C.; Spivak, Lawrence Edmund.; Stein, Robert, 1924-2014; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958.; Stout, Rex, 1886-1975.; Stuber, Stanley I. (Stanley Irving), 1903-1985; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.; Susskind, David, 1920-1987; Taft, Charles P. (Charles Phelps), 1897-1983; Tate, Jack B., 1902-; Taussig, Charles William, 1896-1948.; Tead, Ordway, 1891-1973.; Terman, Lewis Madison, 1877-1956.; Thayer, Walter N. (Walter Nelson), 1910-1989; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Ulich, Robert, 1890-1977; Vallée, Rudy, 1901-1986; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975.; Viereck, Peter, 1916-2006; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949.; Wakefield, Sherman Day, 1894-1971.; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974.; Weeks, Edward Augustus, 1898-; Wendt, Gerald, 1891-; Whitaker, Arthur Preston, 1895-1979.; Williams, Charl Ormond, 1885-1969; Woodfolk, Josiah Pitts, 1894-; Wylie, Philip, 1902-1971.; Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
Sound Recording Terms
Blanshard, Paul, 1892-1980; Americans United for Separation of Church and State.; Church and state--United States.; Catholic Church--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Bennett, John C. (John Coleman), 1902-1995; O'Gara, James Vincent, 1918-; Kunstler, William M. (William Moses), 1919-1995
- Correspondence 1892-1973
  The Correspondence series is dated 1892 to 1973 and is arranged chronologically. Most of the letters date in the period of 1947 to 1969 when Blanshard was a full-time professional writer. The content of the letters relates to his research and writing, especially to the topic of the Catholic Church in America. A selective index to Blanshard's correspondents has been prepared and is appended to this finding aid.
  - 1892, 1903, 1914-1915, 1928 (Box 1)
    [1-1]
  - 1932-1933, 1937, 1940 (Box 1)
    [1-2]
  - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    [1-3]
  - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    [l-4]
  - January-June, 1947 (Box 1)
    [1-5]
  - July-October, 1947 (Box 1)
    [1-6]
  - November-December, 1947 (Box 1)
    [1-7]
  - circa 1948 (Box 1)
    [l-8]
  - January-February, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-9]
  - March-April, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-10]
  - May-June, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-11]
  - July-August, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-12]
  - September, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-13]
  - October, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-14]
  - November, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-15]
  - December, 1948 (Box 1)
    [1-16]
  - circa 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-17]
  - January, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-18]
  - February, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-19]
  - March, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-20]
  - April, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-21]
  - May 1-15, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-22]
  - May 16-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-23]
  - June, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-24]
  - July 1-10, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-25]
  - July 11-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-26]
  - August 1-15, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-27]
  - August 16-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-28]
  - September 1-19, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-29]
  - September 20-25, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-30]
  - September 26-30, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-31]
  - October 1-10, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-32]
  - October 11-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-33]
  - November 1-13, 1949 (Box 1)
    [l-34]
  - November 14-30, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-35]
  - December 1-17, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-36]
  - December 18-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    [1-37]
  - January, 1950 (Box 1)
    [l-38]
  - February, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-39]
  - March, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-40]
  - April, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-41]
  - May 1-12, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-42]
  - May 13-31, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-43]
  - June 1-15, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-44]
  - June 16-30, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-45]
  - July 1-25, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-46]
  - July 26-31-August, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-47]
  - September, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-48]
  - October-November, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-49]
  - December, 1950 (Box 1)
    [1-50]
  - January, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-1]
  - February 1-15, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-2]
  - February 16-28, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-3]
  - March, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-4]
  - April, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-5]
  - May 1-19, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-6]
  - May 20-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-7]
  - June 1-14, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-8]
  - June 15-30, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-9]
  - July 1-17, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-10]
  - July 18-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-11]
  - August 1-15, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-12]
  - August 16-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-13]
  - September 1-18, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-14]
  - September 19-30, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-15]
  - October 1-15, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-16]
  - October 16-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-17]
  - November, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-18]
  - December 1-19, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-19]
  - December 20-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    [2-20]
  - January-February, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-21]
  - March, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-22]
  - April, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-23]
  - May-June, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-24]
  - July-October, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-25]
  - November-December, 1952 (Box 2)
    [2-26]
  - January-February, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-27]
  - March, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-28]
  - April, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-29]
  - May, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-30]
  - June 1-17, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-31]
  - June 18-30, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-32]
  - July-August, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-33]
  - September-October, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-34]
  - November 1-11, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-35]
  - November 12-30, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-36]
  - December 1-7, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-37]
  - December 8-31, 1953 (Box 2)
    [2-38]
  - January, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-39]
  - February-March, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-40]
  - April-May, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-41]
  - June 1-8, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-42]
  - June 9-30, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-43]
  - July, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-44]
  - August, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-45]
  - September 1-19, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-46]
  - September 20-30, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-47]
  - October-November, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-48]
  - December, 1954 (Box 2)
    [2-49]
  - January 1-10, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-50]
  - January 11-31, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-51]
  - February, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-52]
  - March, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-53]
  - April, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-54]
  - May, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-55]
  - June, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-56]
  - July, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-57]
  - August, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-58]
  - September 1-12, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-59]
  - September 13-30, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-60]
  - October-December, 1955 (Box 2)
    [2-61]
  - January, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-1]
  - February, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-2]
  - March, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-3]
  - April, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-4]
  - May, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-5]
  - June, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-6]
  - July 1-18, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-7]
  - July 19-31, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-8]
  - August, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-9]
  - September, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-10]
  - October-November, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-11]
  - December, 1956 (Box 3)
    [3-12]
  - January, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-13]
  - February-March, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-14]
  - April, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-15]
  - May, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-16]
  - June, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-17]
  - July, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-18]
  - August 1-10, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-19]
  - August 11-31, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-20]
  - September-October, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-21]
  - November-December, 1957 (Box 3)
    [3-22]
  - January, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-23]
  - February-March, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-24]
  - April 1-14, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-25]
  - April 15-30, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-26]
  - May, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-27]
  - June, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-28]
  - July, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-29]
  - August 1-21, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-30]
  - August 22-31, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-31]
  - September, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-32]
  - October, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-33]
  - November, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-34]
  - December, 1958 (Box 3)
    [3-35]
  - January, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-36]
  - February, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-37]
  - March-April, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-38]
  - May-July, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-39]
  - August-October, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-40]
  - November, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-41]
  - December, 1959 (Box 3)
    [3-42]
  - January, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-43]
  - February, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-44]
  - March, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-45]
  - April-May, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-46]
  - June-July, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-47]
  - August, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-48]
  - September, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-49]
  - October-December, 1960 (Box 3)
    [3-50]
  - January-February, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-51]
  - March-May, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-52]
  - June, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-53]
  - July 1-18, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-54]
  - July 19-31, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-55]
  - August, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-56]
  - September, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-57]
  - October-December, 1961 (Box 3)
    [3-58]
  - January-March, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-l]
  - April, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-2]
  - May, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-3]
  - June, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-4]
  - July, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-5]
  - August, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-6]
  - September-October, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-7]
  - November, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-8]
  - December, 1962 (Box 4)
    [4-9]
  - January-February, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-10]
  - March-May, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-11]
  - June-July, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-12]
  - August-September, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-13]
  - October, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-14]
  - November-December, 1963 (Box 4)
    [4-15]
  - January-February, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-16]
  - March-April, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-17]
  - May-June, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-18]
  - July-August, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-19]
  - September, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-20]
  - October-November, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-21]
  - December, 1964 (Box 4)
    [4-22]
  - January-February, 1965 (Box 4)
    [4-23]
  - March-May, 1965 (Box 4)
    [4-24]
  - June-July, 1965 (Box 4)
    [4-25]
  - August-December, 1965 (Box 4)
    [4-26]
  - January-February, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-27]
  - March, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-28]
  - April, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-29]
  - May-June, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-30]
  - July-August, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-31]
  - September-December, 1966 (Box 4)
    [4-32]
  - January-April, 1967 (Box 4)
    [4-33]
  - May-December, 1967 (Box 4)
    [4-34]
  - January-March, 1968 (Box 4)
    [4-35]
  - April-July, 1968 (Box 4)
    [4-36]
  - August-December, 1968 (Box 4)
    [4-37]
  - January-April, 1969 (Box 4)
    [4-38]
  - May-December, 1969 (Box 4)
    [4-39]
  - 1970-1973 (Box 4)
    [4-40]
- Writings and related materials circa 1917-1978
  The largest series in the collection is Writings and Related Materials. This series is further divided into six subseries: Articles and Speeches; Book Reviews; Journal Articles; Books and pamphlets; Background Files and Post Publication Files for Blanshard Books; and Background materials for speeches and articles.
  - Articles and Speeches
    - 1917